<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>publishing on Gabriel&#39;s Virtual Tavern</title>
    <link>https://jorenjoestar.github.io/categories/publishing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in publishing on Gabriel&#39;s Virtual Tavern</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 15:46:28 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://jorenjoestar.github.io/categories/publishing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Year of the Vulkan Book</title>
      <link>https://jorenjoestar.github.io/post/year_of_the_vulkan_book/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 15:46:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jorenjoestar.github.io/post/year_of_the_vulkan_book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! How have you been ?&lt;br&gt;
A little more than a year has passed since my last post, but for a good reason!&lt;br&gt;
Last year was all dedicated to writing this book, &lt;strong&gt;Mastering Graphics Programming with Vulkan&lt;/strong&gt;, available in different countries on Amazon &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Mastering-Graphics-Programming-Vulkan-state/dp/1803244798&#34;&gt;US&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Mastering-Graphics-Programming-Vulkan-state/dp/1803244798&#34;&gt;UK&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.in/Mastering-Graphics-Programming-Vulkan-state/dp/1803244798&#34;&gt;India&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.it/Mastering-Graphics-Programming-Vulkan-state/dp/1803244798&#34;&gt;Italy&lt;/a&gt; and many more, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/marco_castorina&#34;&gt;Marco Castorina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
All my coding free time went into the writing of this book with him, and this post is a little recap of what happened behind the scenes and my experience of writing a book for the first time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-it-started&#34;&gt;How it started&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started thanks to this blog!&lt;br&gt;
At the end of 2021 Marco wrote to me if I was interested to collaborate, in any form we would agree, on writing a book about Vulkan.&lt;br&gt;
Thanks to the articles I wrote here and the code on Github he wanted to know if I could help.&lt;br&gt;
We jumped on a Skype call and talked: since the beginning there was a good feeling talking to him. My gut instict was right!&lt;br&gt;
He asked me in which way I wanted to help him, including being a co-author&amp;hellip;and me being me, I thought &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve never wrote a book, this could be an amazing experience!&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br&gt;
So we agreed that we will write the book together, and from there he introduced me to the team at Packt and we started discussing about the topics.&lt;br&gt;
One thing we really wanted to do is to dedicate time learning topics that we did not have time to study, and that was a huge risk but also a great reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some talking with Packt, we agreed on a 9 months writing time: a tight schedule, but we felt we could make it working together with Marco.&lt;br&gt;
We succedeed, albeit not to the level we wanted, but it was a huge learning experience for both of us (I am pretty sure is the same for Marco).&lt;br&gt;
In this case I measure success as a combination of effort, learning new things, delivering and enjoyment of the process.&lt;br&gt;
As you will see later on in this post, this book is far from perfect and make me question a better way of delivering the rendering knowledge we wanted to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-purpose-of-the-book&#34;&gt;The purpose of the book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning we had clear in mind that we needed to show how to use Vulkan in a real, modern and AAA rendering context.&lt;br&gt;
Both Marco and me work in the industry, and we decided to try to create a package that included the latest rendering tech that you would find in a AAA renderer.
We knew we could not possibly deliver a bulletproof technology written in few months writing code after work, but at least we could give some pointers to what is used right now.&lt;br&gt;
We also wanted to demistify Vulkan and show it in a practical full-blown demo. In this sense, after reading some reviews, I think we did not hit the mark - many complains are that we used a reincarnation of the Hydra engine, stripped down to accomodate a Vulkan only mindset.&lt;br&gt;
We will talk about that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, if I can simplify everything in one phrase, it would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demistification of Vulkan as an API and its application to modern rendering techniques&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;choosing-the-topics&#34;&gt;Choosing the topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was actually a very fun part!&lt;br&gt;
Both me and Marco wanted to explore and write some techniques from scratch.&lt;br&gt;
We started with asking ourselves which techniques a modern rendering engine supports, based on our work knowledge, and started jotting down those.&lt;br&gt;
There also some techniques that we singularly never did, and we tried to do what we would have most fun doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a simple list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pure bindless mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frame graph based&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clustered Deferred Rendering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point lights with cubemap shadows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mesh shaders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GPU driven rendering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temporal Anti-Aliasing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volumetric Fog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raytracing: shadows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global Illumination&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this list we started writing collecting links to the various topics before the next big decision&amp;hellip;where do we start from a code pespective ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;choosing-an-engine&#34;&gt;Choosing an engine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We always knew we wanted to use the thinnest layer on top of Vulkan.&lt;br&gt;
We explored various libraries, but something was clear: we need to learn how to use those libraries as well, and that would mean some time.&lt;br&gt;
After some thoughts&amp;hellip;we chose to take Hydra, my own creature ehm engine, and cleanup some code, make the API Vulkan only and use that.&lt;br&gt;
Hydra is the foundation for the code of all the articles on this blog, and already the only backend working was Vulkan.&lt;br&gt;
Some could argue that this is not the best choice, but actually we have two advantages: first, having written it from scratch I knew every nook and crannies of the code; second it has a lot of boilerplate code for Vulkan and for other simple but useful subsystems (cameras, input, &amp;hellip;).&lt;br&gt;
Another choice we made was to go fully Vulkan based: GLSL was the default choice for writing shaders, using JSON files to create a smaller Techniques/FX framework, and even better&amp;hellip;parsing SpirV to take informations about the pipeline!&lt;br&gt;
Marco came out with this idea, and I really liked it.&lt;br&gt;
Between all the different skills he has, he is great in reading the Vulkan specifications and use them.&lt;br&gt;
And with these choices&amp;hellip;all was set to begin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-structure-the-code&#34;&gt;How to structure the code?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was another big decision to make.&lt;br&gt;
We thought a lot about it: we wanted a way to freeze the code in time for each chapter, but we didn&amp;rsquo;t want to rely on github history to do that.&lt;br&gt;
The natural evolution of this thought is to create the code for each chapter in a separate folder.&lt;br&gt;
So we separated the code in the common code area, where code between different chapters is shared, and the rendering code went into each chapter.&lt;br&gt;
This included both shaders and the core rendering code. 
The current structure of code is something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;source&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
__&lt;strong&gt;chapter1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
____&lt;strong&gt;graphics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
__&lt;strong&gt;raptor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
____&lt;strong&gt;application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
____&lt;strong&gt;foundation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main raptor folder contains foundation and application subfolders: &lt;strong&gt;application&lt;/strong&gt; is contains a high level wrapper for window, input and application so that it is easier to fire a working application, while &lt;strong&gt;foundation&lt;/strong&gt; the main data structures (array and hash map) and some utility functions/subsystems (like file management, string buffers, time queries, memory management, logging, gltf parsing, camera&amp;hellip;).&lt;br&gt;
All the code in these folders is shared between chapters, so we duplicate and evolve only the rendering part, as it is the main focus of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was it perfect ?&lt;br&gt;
Absolutely not.&lt;br&gt;
Was it painful ?&lt;br&gt;
Yes, a little.
Could we do better ?
Absolutely yes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many problems with these choices, but at the end it worked for us: for every chapter you have a snapshot of the rendering code, while everthing else that is not rendering related is unchanged, and should actually not be the focus.&lt;br&gt;
There are some big downsides: for example every time we would add something to a chapter, we would need to port the code to the following chapters. Fixing a bug in chapter 4 meant porting it up to the 15th chapter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same is happening now that the code is in the wild: when we receive a bugfix, we need to port it to all subsequent chapters.&lt;br&gt;
Again not the best choice, but the best with our knowledge at the time we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-awesomeness-of-having-a-publisher&#34;&gt;The awesomeness of having a publisher&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never worked with a publisher, but working with Packt was a great experience.&lt;br&gt;
They gave us the power to concentrate only on writing the book and the code, without worrying about anything else.&lt;br&gt;
Printing, delivering, organizing, they really took care of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we thought we were late, or we needed more time, they listened as well.&lt;br&gt;
They also knew that the time to write a book was crucial, as this book covers a missing piece of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every feedback on both sides was thoughtful and well received, so it was a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all the team behind Packt, we managed to have a deep focus on working on our side of things and only on that.&lt;br&gt;
That was great to experience!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;lessons&#34;&gt;Lessons&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole journey has been powerful and helped me navigating some personal difficult times as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-power-of-deadlines&#34;&gt;The power of deadlines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I love to have projects in my free time, because I can explore what I want, even if just redoing the same thing just in a completely different way.&lt;br&gt;
Problem is that not having a fixed objective can make me feel lost sometimes, same for not having any timeline.&lt;br&gt;
Articles in this blog helped that, but the book is the ultimate example!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deadlines gives you that huge lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the best that you can, with the resources you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources include both knowledge and time.&lt;br&gt;
In the realm of knowledge I include not only technical knowledge, but also personal knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problems-of-deadlines&#34;&gt;The problems of deadlines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deadlines have also an uncomfortable side with it.&lt;br&gt;
We did not manage to put everything we wanted into the code, for example shader reloading, code generation, local tonemapping, and many many more.&lt;br&gt;
Deadlines really push you to think about what you can and cannot achieve given the time.&lt;br&gt;
And many times you over or underestimate the time, and have to change priorities.&lt;br&gt;
This is one of the biggest problems with game development, as there are many unknowns unknowns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, you need to deliver, thus you can&amp;rsquo;t loose too much time thinking and writing code in the best way possible.&lt;br&gt;
You deliver, and this is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the time we put on this book was our free time, after a day of work, or in the weekend, so possibly at times you had to figure out things with very low energies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every piece of code we were writing, this was the question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this that I am doing really necessary given the time I have ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;know-thyself&#34;&gt;Know thyself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another great lesson is that before writing a book, there is one &amp;lsquo;persona&amp;rsquo; - Gabriel - that is writing the book.&lt;br&gt;
Do you listen to yourself ? To your needs ? Are you ready to know Gabriel with a new perspective, as the writer of a book ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These can seem like crazy questions, but our identity changes a bit depending on the context.&lt;br&gt;
Who do you think you are when writing a book ?&lt;br&gt;
Are you overconfident ? Underconfident (not sure this word exists) ?&lt;br&gt;
Are you ready to change your mindset on a technical topic ?&lt;br&gt;
Are you ready to do something wrong and being called out for that ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one of our superpowers is the possibility to change perspective based on experience.&lt;br&gt;
Even if it is painful: seeing that you don&amp;rsquo;t know enough about a topic that you should know, after all this year of rendering, can be painful.&lt;br&gt;
As candid as I can be, there are still many topics that I don&amp;rsquo;t know deeply, nor I understand fully.&lt;br&gt;
That is what I love about rendering: is such a huge topic, that really puts your ego in check.&lt;br&gt;
I will always know less than a year before, where multiple people are researching and advancing the knowledge.&lt;br&gt;
But still, I can help crafting amazing games and rendering tech!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the relationship with our reality is what matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the biggest lessons about writing this book: the combination of effort, changing perspective and mindset is the real win.&lt;br&gt;
And on that topic, I have no regrets: we acted at our best given the constraints.&lt;br&gt;
But we can do better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you ready to change perspective in front of new inputs ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;technical-knowledge&#34;&gt;Technical knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a digression about the human side of things (I would talk about that for hours&amp;hellip;) let&amp;rsquo;s get back to the technical knowledge.&lt;br&gt;
What I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt is that&amp;hellip;I did not know many new topics, only read about it, and by actually doing them I have a better understanding.&lt;br&gt;
Ultimate understanding ?&lt;br&gt;
Not even close!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, re-writing or re-implementing a technique makes me understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found over and over that reading a paper or some code does not work much for me.&lt;br&gt;
I can have an idea about something, but re-doing is what makes me create my mental model of it.&lt;br&gt;
Some have the power to learn by just reading or hearing, not me.&lt;br&gt;
That is why I am also active in my free time: real knowledge comes from models arising from experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-thinnest-vulkan-layer-possible&#34;&gt;The thinnest Vulkan layer possible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a post-launch thought, and one of the most common critiques I&amp;rsquo;ve read around about the book.&lt;br&gt;
Many did not like the usage of Hydra/Raptor, and complained that this was too much of a &amp;lsquo;Raptor manual&amp;rsquo; instead of a pure Vulkan book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could have we written a thinner layer ?&lt;br&gt;
I think we could have done it, and it would be an interesting challenge for the future.&lt;br&gt;
I still stand with our choice, as I think the abstraction we provided is so thin that does not change the API understanding, but actually elevates it to a more common &amp;lsquo;next generation APIs&amp;rsquo; mindset and knowledge that will help on using Vulkan, DirectX12, consoles API and such.&lt;br&gt;
Still I get it: this is a Vulkan book, so you should focus on Vulkan only!&lt;br&gt;
Maybe is the fact that, even though I&amp;rsquo;ve used (and written from scratch) Vulkan renderers in the past, I can&amp;rsquo;t help but seeing a pattern in the all APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end rendering is a combination of big concepts, that are present in both Vulkan and DirectX12, like Images, Buffers, Pipelines, Swapchains, Command Buffers and such.&lt;br&gt;
Once you master these concepts, you can use those on any API.&lt;br&gt;
Yet with Raptor the usage is a slightly higher level compared to simple Vulkan, but I really feel still now that helps visualizing what is happening even better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that some areas, like descriptor sets and pipeline management can be too Raptory, but still it would have been a problem to fix anyway, even with simple Vulkan: this bookeeping is that you don&amp;rsquo;t find many times in tutorials around, but what gives you the power to develop complex techniques without writing a ton of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am (slowly) in the active process of trying to strip even more layering to have a simpler Vulkan, so I am happy about this critique.&lt;br&gt;
I will learn something new, and maybe next edition, if will ever exists, will be an even more barebone Vulkan code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there a way to write organized Vulkan code that is evern more straight-forward ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-joy-of-exploration&#34;&gt;The joy of exploration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing the book, for each chapter we first wrote the code to be working to a good level, then we would write the corresponding chapter and fix/improve the code after.&lt;br&gt;
This was an interesting way of working, really focused on having something measurable and usable before writing any sentence about a chapter.&lt;br&gt;
With Marco we decided to put a lot of current topics, like Raytracing, Temporal Anti-Aliasing, Bindless, Mesh shaders and such, so that we could have a go at implementing them all together.&lt;br&gt;
There are better implementations out there, but I think we delivered a solid demo in the final chapter, that showcases all those together in harmony.&lt;br&gt;
During the development, I would ask myself multiple times:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you enjoying the exploration ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often times when navigating uncharted territories, we are stressed out about it. And I was many times, but this question really helped me not reaching the breaking point.&lt;br&gt;
I still need to enjoy the process, otherwise what is the point of it ?&lt;br&gt;
It was not always possible, and sometimes you have to grind through it, but still it was great.&lt;br&gt;
Having Marco as an ally, and a friend, helped a lot.&lt;br&gt;
When any of the two was stuck, or tired, the other would come in and help.&lt;br&gt;
We went with the flow, we worked together on some chapters, and singularly on others.&lt;br&gt;
We talked and I shared also my personal difficulties, as 2022 was a though year: useful, but though.&lt;br&gt;
And when we were stressed, or tired, we would talk about that.&lt;br&gt;
Never forget about the human behind the role!&lt;br&gt;
I really enjoyed working with him!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rendering-is-about-synergies&#34;&gt;Rendering is about synergies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more chapters we wrote, the more I thought how rendering is a beautiful synergy, and that is why re-creating a renderer visuals is hard.&lt;br&gt;
Every pass in a frame needs to find its space in other passes as well (well not every one of them).&lt;br&gt;
It is an orchestra of GPU programs, textures, buffers and pipelines that create beautiful pixels.&lt;br&gt;
Building each chapter with something more really shaped this.&lt;br&gt;
Again, it could have been done in a better way, yes!&lt;br&gt;
But the effort and the knowledge at the time, plus the time constraints, are all that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I am happy with the result: we forged something that, albeit not being perfect, really touched a little of everything you find in a modern renderer. Something you will not find in a tech demo, that shows just a portion of this.&lt;br&gt;
Once we&amp;rsquo;ve added Clustered Deferred rendering, we added pointlights shadows (with the vertex/mesh shader only output) then we built on top Volumetric Fog, and TAA, and then started exploring indirect lighting with ray tracing&amp;hellip;everything worked together.&lt;br&gt;
Re-using the clustered light structure to read lights into the Volumetric Fog for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did it step by step, trying to show the way.&lt;br&gt;
For each step, the question was always:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is this technique adding to the scene ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We always had an eye for performances as well, even though having a 2070 did not help :p&lt;br&gt;
But still, as you see opening the demo, there is a GPU profiler that gives you a frame timing breakdown and helps keeping track of where the time budget is going.&lt;br&gt;
This is a game developer mindset: always think about performances.&lt;br&gt;
To create realtime-usable tech, you need it to be fast, or at least keep the total frame time to an acceptable level!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve touched a lot of topics in this post, and I will gladly talk more about this stuff.&lt;br&gt;
One thing is clear: I learnt a lot, both technically and personally, and I will continue to learn more.&lt;br&gt;
There are other things on the horizon sparked by this book, like a talk about Vulkan at Eurographics 2023, or the idea of doing a &amp;lsquo;write your modern renderer&amp;rsquo; in italian, my native language, and more.&lt;br&gt;
For sure a lot of feedback and things to evolve and experiment, and I am thankful for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wish that we could help streamlining the usage of Vulkan, maybe developing some lightweight library to help developers (like the Vulkan Memory Allocator), but let&amp;rsquo;s see the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now I enjoy the experience that the book gave me, the many lessons, the knowledge and the thought that I can still improve and learn, while remembering to enjoy the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
